A Guide to the Frederic G. Melcher-Robert Frost Collection,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series V: Correspondence of Frederic G. Melcher with Various Authors and Publishers
  - Lawrance Thompson, recently out of the Navy, asks Melcher for his help in gathering materials for his biography of Robert Frost, 1946-1949 (Box-folder 6:54)
    Lawrance Thompson, recently out of the Navy, asks Melcher for his help in gathering materials for his biography of Robert Frost, and mentions living in one of Frost's many farmhouses in Vermont at Ripton while he spent time with Frost who described the experience as "walking around the story of my life" (October 10, 1946); Melcher mentions the collection of Charles R. Green and the records made by Columbia University of Robert Frost reading his poetry (October 14, 1946); Thompson agrees as to the importance of preserving the prose of Robert Frost because he fears that Frost will never get around to doing anything about it, particularly the Charles Eliot Norton lectures (October 17, 21, 1946); promises to bring Melcher some items for his collection and finds his information about August Gehrs' recollections on the sale of North of Boston most interesting (November 5, 7, 1946); and supplies gossip about the title of Frost's next book (November 12, 15, 1946). He especially appreciates the use of Melcher's copy of Rural America because it contains Frost's article "Poetry and the Rural Life." Thompson feels that this article "is his own careful statement that he isn't trying to get everybody back to the farm; he is merely trying to get people to realize the importance of being themselves, and cultivating an Emersonian self-reliance, and by analogy the farm offers a symbol of the kind of withdrawal-from-society in order to get time to strengthen self and create produce for the open market." He also expresses concern about the preservation of original documents, sharing how two of the persons he contacted about Frost letters had lost them to fire (December 2, 1946). Thompson thanks Melcher for letting him read the Frost-Melcher correspondence and the excerpt from Publishers' Weekly for January 22, 1916 about Frost and for all of his additional help on his biography (January 4, 194[7?]); sends a list of detailed questions generated by looking at Melcher's material on Frost which Melcher attempts to answer point by point before going on his trip to Japan in the interest of copyright treaty drafting (February 3, 4, 1947).
  - Ridgely Torrence responds to the invitation to the Robert Frost dinner, 1925 Mar 13 (Box-folder 6:55)
    "I value him as a friend and I admire his poetry extremely. His light seems to me one of the most authentic among living poets. Everything he writes interests me. I admire equally too, his spiritual honesty and solid sincerity."
  - Unidentified Correspondents discuss such topics as: soldiers' reading (August 5, 1918), 1902-1948, n.d. (Box-folder 6:56)
    Ten suggestions for the White House library (June 26, 1934); the pen portrait in the January 17th issue of Publishers' Weekly about his 48 years of publishing, Ben, Houghton Mifflin Company (January 26, 1948); British publisher, [George?] Allen, expresses an appreciation for Melcher's contributions to the world of books, reflection on his own third of a century in publishing and enjoyment of the occasion honoring him (June 8, n.y.).
  - Louis Untermeyer discusses the invitation to the Robert Frost birthday dinner and related details (1925); and thanks for the information that he sent him for an article in The American Spectator (October 9, 1932). 1925, 1932 (Box-folder 6:57)
  - Sir Stanley Unwin (1884-1968), George Allen & Unwin Ltd. agrees to accept Melcher's son, Daniel, as a volunteer in his office, 1934-1946 (Box-folder 6:58)
    Sir Stanley Unwin (1884-1968), George Allen and Unwin Ltd. agrees to accept Melcher's son, Daniel, as a volunteer in his office with the warning that he will arrive at very busy time in their organization; mentions other European publishers where he could volunteer; and mentions the copyright bill in Congress (August 23, 1934; March 18, 1935); and he discusses his Knighthood and his work on behalf of the National Book Council (January 28, 1946).
  - D.B. Updike, The Merrymount Press, regrets that he did not get a chance to say good-bye when Melcher left Lauriat's for W.K. Stewart & Co., Booksellers, Indianapolis, Indiana (March 10, 1913), 1913-1940 (Box-folder 6:59)
    Mentions examples from his press illustrating the good type of work done there (January 13, 1915); discusses Mr. Benton's paper on Baskerville, The Life of Baskerville by Strauss, and the Bibliography of Baskerville published by the Baskerville Club (January 15, 1915); appreciates the kind words about The Merrymount Press in Publishers' Weekly (September 7, 1925); Melcher expresses his pleasure at a gift of a volume from the Humanist Library (April 1, 1927); appreciates the dinner given for him at the University Club (May 8, 12, 23, 1928); feels incapable of speaking gracefully or well at a presentation of an award to Mr. Kent (December 28, 1929); agrees to sit for a photograph by Mrs. Ullman, but he doesn't like to have his photograph taken (November 18, 1930); refuses to speak before the American Institute of Graphic Arts (February 20, 1931); and thanks Melcher for his "very handsome editorial" in the Publishers' Weekly of March 23rd (March 26, 1940).
  - Carl Van Doren, The Nation, agrees to speak at Montclair, New Jersey on Today's Novelists (July 20, 1922); and discusses his book The Ninth Wave (September 13, 1926). 1922, 1926 (Box-folder 6:60)
  - Irita Van Doren writes about arranging speakers for the Robert Frost birthday dinner. 1925 Feb 19 (Box-folder 6:61)
  - Mark Van Doren accepts the invitation to the Robert Frost birthday dinner. 1925 Mar 3 (Box-folder 6:62)
  - John C. Van Dyke refuses an invitation to speak before the National Arts Club (November 9, 1923). 1923 Nov 9 (Box-folder 6:63)
  - Hendrik Willen Van Loon sends a hand-drawn and colored post card about his book Ancient Man the Beginning of Civilizations (November 25, 1920), 1920-1940 (Box-folder 6:64)
    Discusses the suspicion of the foreigner in America (May 30, 1922); and his book written for the Book Fair ([June] 15, 1937).
  - John W. Vandercook agrees to speak at Lake Mohonk and asks advice as to a topic (July 4, 1934; n.d.), 1934, n.d. (Box-folder 6:65)
  - Dorothy M. Vaughan, Librarian, Portsmouth, New Hampshire, writes concerning an oil painting of the ship Frank Jones, 1949 Dec 12 (Box-folder 6:66)
    Dorothy M. Vaughan, Librarian, Portsmouth, New Hampshire, writes concerning an oil painting of the ship Frank Jones, which she suggests that Melcher may wish to purchase for the library as a memorial to the Melcher family of Portsmouth. She also tells of finding a newspaper account of the Franklin statue dedication held in Boston in 1856 which mentions that the old Melcher press was sent up for the occasion. She believes this proves that the old John Melcher press belonged to Benjamin Franklin.
  - Elizabeth Gray Vining thanks Melcher for his letter of praise as one with a sympathetic understanding of Japan. 1952 May 17 (Box-folder 6:67)
  - Robert F. Wagner, Office of the Mayor of New York, thanks Melcher for attending luncheon to discuss the development of Carnegie Hall as a permanent cultural center. 1960 Oct 10 (Box-folder 6:68)
  - Lillian D. Wald recommends for reading Goodbye Mr. Chips. 1935 Jan 8 (Box-folder 6:69)
  - mery Walker accepts the request for him to sell the American periodical rights in his article in The Times Printing Supplement, 1929 Nov 1 (Box-folder 6:70)
  - Harry [Warren ?] asks if he can't get on the free list for receipt of Publishers' Weekly. 1930 Apr 17 (Box-folder 6:71)
  - Booker T. Washington, two autographs, one on a calling card 1901 (Box-folder 6:72)
  - Rose Weinberg thanks Melcher for sharing his notes about the [Herbert] Putnam celebration in [1949?] n.y. Apr 19 (Box-folder 6:73)
  - John Hall Wheelock is unable to accept the invitation to the Robert Frost birthday dinner. 1925 Feb 28 (Box-folder 6:74)
  - W.A. White is unable to recommend a book for reading as he feels "There is no one book for every man." 1935 Jan 2 (Box-folder 6:75)
  - Edgar Swan Wiers, minister of Unity Church, Montclair, New Jersey, expresses his gratitude for his work as presiding officer where he "unified everything and gave an emotional content without letting that go too far." 1931 Mar 27 (Box-folder 6:76)
  - Ray Lyman Wilbur invites Melcher to become a member of the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection (July 7, 14, 1930); and recommends for reading The Challenge to Liberty by Herbert Hoover (January 2, 1935). 1930, 1935 (Box-folder 6:77)
  - John Gilbert Winant (1889-1947) thanks Melcher for the memorial book on President Roosevelt, 1945 Aug 13 (Box-folder 6:78)
  - Robert Winthrop (1809-1894) to the Rev. Walter S. Alexander, sends autographs of Mr. Webster and Mr. Choate. 1868 Dec 9 (Box-folder 6:79)
  - Humbert Wolfe asks Melcher to visit him sometime in London. n.d. (Box-folder 6:80)
  - Alexander Woollcott discusses an invitation to speak at the annual luncheon of the National Association of Book Publishers. 1932 Jan 8, 12 (Box-folder 6:81)
  - Elinor Wylie sends payment for the Robert Frost birthday dinner. 1925 Mar 4 (Box-folder 6:82)